Guide to the Percy Marks Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Percy Marks papers
1900-1961
1920-1940
YCAL MSS 4
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.75
(11 boxes)
The Percy Marks Papers contain manuscripts, correspondence, and personal papers documenting aspects of the life and career of Percy Marks.
Marks, Percy, 1891-1956
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Papers were donated to The Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library by the author's widow, Mrs. Bernard Barton, in November 1962.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Restricted Fragile Papers in boxes 9 and 10 may only be consulted with permission of the appropriate curator. Preservation photocopies for reference use have been substituted in the main files.
PERCY MARKS (1891-1956)
Percy Marks was born in Covelo, California, on September 9, 1891. He received a Bachelor of Letters degree from the University of California at Berkeley in 1912 and a Master of Arts degree from Harvard University in 1914. Over the next decade he served successively as supervisor of education at Tewksbury (Massachusetts) State Infirmary, and as instructor of English at Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Dartmouth College, and Brown University. In 1925 he gave up his teaching career in order to devote himself to writing and lecturing. Between 1925 and 1949 most of his major works were written. In the latter year he resumed teaching as instructor of English and literature at the University of Connecticut at Waterbury, a post he held until shortly before his death.
Marks wrote some twenty books, mostly novels, and contributed short stories and essays to several prominent American literary magazines. His major works include Martha, Lord of Himself, A Tree Grown Straight, And Points Beyond, The Days Are Fled, Between Two Autumns, Knave of Diamonds, Shade of Sycamore, Blair Marriman, The Craft of Writing, and his most famous novel, The Plastic Age.
During World War I, Marks served as second lieutenant in the U.S. Army. He was married to Margaret Ellen Gates in Gardena, California, on December 17, 1927; they had one daughter, Sally Jean. Percy Marks died in New Haven, Connecticut, on December 27, 1956.
For further biographical information, see the National Cyclopadeia of American Biography, Vol. 46, pp. 321-22, as well as folders 131-33 of this collection.
Scope and Contents
The Percy Marks Papers contain manuscripts, correspondence, and personal papers documenting aspects of the life and career of the author of The Plastic Age. The material spans the years 1900 to 1961, with the bulk falling between 1920 and 1950.
The papers are housed in eight boxes and are divided into three series. The bulk of the collection consists of typewritten manuscripts, some original and some carbon copies, of Percy Marks's novels and short stories. Associated with these manuscripts is a considerable amount of fan mail. In addition, there is general correspondence unrelated to literary works and a miscellaneous section of disparate personal papers.
Series I, Writings, is divided into two sections, Books and Shorter Works. Books, which comprises roughly three quarters of the entire collection, is composed primarily of material relating to Marks's novels, but also includes correspondence regarding one of the two classroom textbooks he wrote. Manuscripts for nine of his twenty books are included in the collection: And Points Beyond, Blair Marriman, The Days Are Fled, Full Flood, The Knave of Diamonds, No Steeper Wall, Shade of Sycamore, A Tree Grown Straight, and The Unwilling God. The collection has typed notes but no manuscript for Marks's first novel, The Plastic Age, published during the height of the Roaring Twenties. There are also sixteen folders of fan mail, which reveal the widely varying public reaction to this provocative work. The Beinecke Library owns inscribed first edition copies of many of Marks's works.
The second section, Shorter Works, consists mainly of short stories, but also includes essays, articles, and a book review. Of interest is his essay on Brown University, in which he extols the institution for its traditions and dedication to excellence. Marks was on the faculty of the English Department at Brown when he wrote The Plastic Age.
Within this series, material related to a specific literary work is grouped in the following order: notes, manuscripts, fan mail, reviews, and publicity, although not all types of material are included for every work. Some manuscripts contain penciled changes in the margins, but for the most part these typescripts are carbons of final copies sent to the publisher.
Series II, Correspondence, consists primarily of personal and professional letters written to Marks, with a few copies of replies. Of interest are letters from family members, personal and professional friends, publishers, critics, authors, and former professors. The oldest item in the series is a letter from Marks's mother, written while he was a student at the University of California. The correspondence of Paul R. Reynolds, Marks's publisher during the twenties, provides insight into the author's successes and failures during the first decade of his career. Isabel Paterson, critic for the New York Herald Tribune during the twenties, writes a letter challenging Marks's philosophy on education and culture. Literary correspondents include Carl Van Doren (1 letter), Upton Sinclair (2 letters), and H.L. Mencken (24 letters). The letters of Van Doren and Sinclair make reference to recent publications by Marks. The letters of Mencken, written for the most part while he was an editor at The Smart Set and The American Mercury, cover a twenty-three-year period and present some insightful comments on Marks's works. Until their deaths, Marks maintained correspondence with L. B. R. Briggs and Bliss Perry, two of his professors at Harvard.
Series III, Personal Papers, is divided into three sections. The first section, Biographical Material, contains numerous obituaries of Marks, as well as such disparate items as a poem, entitled "Susan Brown," written by Marks around the age of nine, his World War I draft card, and a diploma from the University of California, Berkeley. The second section, Photographs, contains one photograph each of Marks's mother and father, and eight of the author. The third section, Textbook, contains a copy of a cherished classroom textbook on English poetry used by Marks at Berkeley.
Authors, American; Best sellers; Briggs, Le Baron Russell, 1855-1934; Marks, Percy, 1891-1956; Mencken, H. L. (Henry Louis), 1880-1956; Perry, Bliss, 1860-1954; Reynolds, Paul Revere, 1864-1944; Brown University
- Writings, 1915-61; Series I; 2.5; (6 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Boxes 1-6 contain Series I, Writings, which is divided into two sections, Books and Shorter Works. Both sections are arranged alphabetically by title and under title according to the hierarchy: notes, manuscripts, fan mail, reviews, and publicity. Fan mail that does not relate to any single work is placed at the end of each section.
  - BOOKS
    - And Points Beyond
      - Manuscript, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 1-5)
      - Fan mail, 1937-40 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Reviews, 1937-38 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Between Two Autumns
      - Fan mail, 1941-44 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Reviews, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Blair Marriman
      - Manuscript, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 10-14)
      - Reviews, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - The Craft of Writing
      - Fan mail, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - The Days Are Fled
      - Manuscript, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 17-22)
      - Fan mail, 1939-45 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - Reviews, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - A Dead Man Dies
      - Reviews, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Full Flood
      - Manuscript, n.d (Box 2, Folder 26-30)
      - Fan mail, 1942-46 (Box 2, Folder 31)
      - Reviews, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - The Knave of Diamonds
      - Manuscript, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 33-35)
      - Fan mail, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Martha
      - Fan mail, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - No Steeper Wall
      - Manuscript, first draft (incomplete), n.d. (Box 3, Folder 38)
      - Manuscript, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 39-45)
      - Fan mail, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 46)
      - Reviews, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - The Plastic Age
      - Notes, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 48)
      - Fan mail, 1923-30, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 49-64)
      - Reviews, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 65)
    - Shade of Sycamore
      - Manuscript, 1944 (Box 5, Folder 66-70)
      - Fan mail, 1944-45 (Box 5, Folder 71)
      - Reviews, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 72)
    - A Tree Grown Straight
      - Manuscript, 1935 (Box 5, Folder 73-77)
      - Fan mail, 1938-44, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 78)
      - Reviews, 1936-37 (Box 5, Folder 79)
    - The Unwilling God
      - Manuscript, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 80-83)
      - Reviews, 1929 (Box 6, Folder 84)
    - What's a Heaven For
      - Fan mail, 1938-39 (Box 6, Folder 85)
      - Reviews, 1938 (Box 6, Folder 86)
    - Miscellaneous Fan Mail
      - Fan Mail, 1924-51, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 87)
  - SHORTER WORKS
    - "The Blind Date"
      - Manuscript, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 88)
    - "Brown University"
      - Manuscript, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 89)
    - "Dear Enemy"
      - Fan Mail, 1915 (Box 6, Folder 90)
    - "The Guilded Log"
      - Manuscript, 1932 (Box 6, Folder 91)
    - "Hood on His Hands"
      - Manuscript, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 92)
    - "Master of Donald Jamieson (Master of Himself)"
      - Manuscript, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 93)
    - "A Matter of Accent"
      - Manuscript, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 94)
    - "Miss Mooney"
      - Manuscript, 1948 (Box 6, Folder 95)
    - "Muddy Water"
      - Manuscript, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 96)
    - "Nancy Disposes"
      - Manuscript, 1930 (Box 6, Folder 97)
    - "Now and Forever Just"
      - Manuscript, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 98)
      - Fan mail, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 99)
    - "Old Lady Albright"
      - Manuscript and printed version, 1945 (Box 6, Folder 100)
    - "One Swell Airdale"
      - Manuscript, 1930 (Box 6, Folder 101)
      - Fan mail, 1930 (Box 6, Folder 102)
    - "Overworked Words and Trite Phrases"
      - Printed version, 1935 Mar 2 (Box 6, Folder 102a)
    - "Paint and Puffs"
      - Manuscript, 1920 (Box 6, Folder 103)
    - "Retreating Barriers"
      - Fan mail, 1927 (Box 6, Folder 104)
    - Review
      - Nuhn, Ferner, The Wind Blew from the East, 1942 Sep 10 (Box 6, Folder 105)
    - "The Stoughton House"
      - Manuscript, 1924 (Box 6, Folder 106)
    - "What's a Fellow to Do about His Mother?"
      - Manuscript, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 107)
    - "The Wind's Will"
      - Manuscript, 1925 (Box 6, Folder 108)
      - Fan mail, 1925 (Box 6, Folder 109)
    - Miscellaneous Fan Mail
      - Fan mail, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 110)
- Correspondence, 1910-54; Series II; 0.25; (1 box)
  Series II, Correspondence, is alphabetically arranged and unidentified correspondence is placed at the end of the series.
  - Allen, Frederick L., 1924 (Box 7, Folder 111)
  - Andrews, Frank D., 1954 Mar 30
  - Ashbey, George R. (Reg), 1943 Mar 29
  - Benefield, Barry, 1924 Sep 11 (Box 7, Folder 112)
  - Briggs, L. B. R., 1924-32 (Box 7, Folder 113)
  - Brush, Katharine, 1939 Dec 13 (Box 7, Folder 114)
  - Burgess, Eugene S., 1943-44
  - Dallas, John T., 1938 Dec 13 (Box 7, Folder 115)
  - De Voto, Bernard, 1937 Mar 24
  - Hart, Walter Harris, 1913 Dec 12 (Box 7, Folder 116)
  - Hawksley, Clara W., 1942, 1943
  - Howland, Clarke, 1930 Jul 21
  - Jensen, Carl J., 1955 Dec 29 (Box 7, Folder 117)
  - Kapstein, I. J., 1938, 1944 (Box 7, Folder 118)
  - Lamson, Carl, 1939 Nov 16 (Box 7, Folder 119)
  - Lando, Edward, 1938 Oct 19
  - Marks, Emma, 1949 Mar 6 (Box 7, Folder 120)
  - Marks, J. Paul, 1929 Mar 3
  - Marks, Sarah Lando, 1910 May 6
  - Mencken, H. L., 1922-45 (Box 7, Folder 121)
  - Morley, F. V., 1928 Nov 14 (Box 7, Folder 122)
  - Neill, William, 1940 Nov 11 (Box 7, Folder 123)
  - Paterson, Isabel, 1927 May 10 (Box 7, Folder 124)
  - Paxton, Helen and William, 1938
  - Perry, Bliss, 1916-49 (Box 7, Folder 125)
  - Reynolds, Paul R., 1926-30 (Box 7, Folder 126)
  - Seawell, Lucy, 1924 Feb 3 (Box 7, Folder 127)
  - Sinclair, Upton, 1924, 1926
  - Soulé, Elizabeth, 1950 Feb 8
  - Van Doren, Carl, 1938 Oct 15 (Box 7, Folder 128)
  - Wheeler, John N., 1925 Jan 5 (Box 7, Folder 129)
  - Williams, George V., 1943 Oct 10
  - Unidentified, 1938, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 130)
- Personal Papers, 1900-57; Series III; 0.25; (1 box)
  Box 8 contains Series III, Personal Papers, which is divided into three sections, Biographical Material, Photographs, and Textbooks.
  - Biographical material, 1913-57 (Box 8, Folder 131)
  - Photographs
    - Marks, Henry and Sarah Lando, ca. 1900 (Box 8, Folder 132)
    - Marks, Percy, 1910-35 (Box 8, Folder 133)
  - Textbook
    - Gayley, Charles Mills and Clement C. Young, The Principles and Progress of English Poetry, 1905 (Box 8, Folder 134)
- Printed Material, Series IV; 0.25; (1 box)
  - "The Gilded Log," California Monthly, 1932 May; 2 (Box 11, Folder 158-159)
  - "Master of Himself," College Humor, 1936 August (Box 11, Folder 160)
- Restricted Fragile Papers, 0.75; (2 boxes)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Boxes 9 and 10, Restricted Fragile Papers, contain fragile originals. The material is arranged in folder order.
  - Box 3, folders 33-35, 38-45 (Box 9, Folder 135-145)
  - Box 4, folder 48 (Box 10, Folder 146)
  - Box 6, folders 91-92, 95, 97-98, 100-101, 103, 106-108 (Box 10, Folder 147-157)